The Day Naruto Was Born
（九喇嘛）ミナト　お前は　ガキに→
Minato… You intended for your brat to
clean up after your mess, right?
己の尻拭いを
させるつもりだったんだろう？
だから　ガキに
わしの残り半分を封印した。
That's why you sealed
my other half inside him…
わしの半身と協力するようにな。
as if you were confident they would
be able to work together.
（ミナト）九尾…。
Nine Tails…
なら　今さら後悔するな。
Then don't regret it now.
クシナが死んだのは
お前のせいではない。
It's not your fault
that Kushina died.
ガキを人柱力にしたことも
悪いことではない。
And making your brat into
a Jinchuriki wasn't a bad thing either.
世界が　こうなってしまったのを
今　まさに→
Because your brat is trying
to change...
what this world has
become right now.
変えようとしているのが
お前のガキだ。
もう　あのときの赤子ではない。
He's not that
newborn babe anymore.
ちょうど明日で…。
In fact, tomorrow is...
Naruto…
（九喇嘛）ナルト…
ちょっと話がある。　聞け。
Listen up... I need to
tell you something...
（ナルト）あ…　やっぱ
思ったとおりだってばよ。
I knew it! I figured as much.
I can't believe the Ten Tails'
Jinchuriki has such a weakness!
（オビト）十尾の人柱力に→
こんな弱点があったとはな。
《オビト：十尾が入った分
すり抜けもできぬか。
And with Ten Tails inside me,
I can't pass through things either!
うっとうしい…》
How frustrating!
仙人のこれなら　いけんぞ！
（サスケ）仙人の力…。
Sage moves will work!
Sage Power?
ガマの攻撃ってのは　仙術っていう
自然エネルギーを使うんだってばよ。
The toad attacks are Sage Jutsu…
They use Nature Energy.
考えてみりゃ
十尾の力を感じてみたとき→
Come to think of it, when I tried
to sense Ten Tails' power,
自然エネルギーそのものだった。
it was Nature Energy itself.
So you can maybe counter
Nature Energy with Nature Energy.
自然の力には　同じ自然の力で
対抗できるってことかもな。
理屈は　よくわかんねえけど。
Not that I really understand it.
仙術　覚えといてよかったぜ。
I'm just glad I learned
Sage Jutsu! All right!
よ～し！　次は　蛙組手だ！
Next up is Frog Kumite!
《扉間：わしとの飛雷神を
即座に理解し→
He instantly grasped how to use
the Flying Raijin with me...
仙人の力まで身につけている。
and has even mastered
Sage Power.
まるで　兄者とともに
戦っているようだな》
I feel like I'm fighting
alongside Elder Brother!
効いたのは確かだが→
It clearly worked.
But he's recovered already,
and now he's guarding his back.
回復して
後ろを警戒しているようだ。
《うかつに
背中に飛ぶと　消されかねん》
If we teleport behind him carelessly,
we might get erased.
そろそろ　月読の準備をし
掃除もしておくか。
I should start preparing for
the Tsukuyomi.
Let's tidy things up.
この現実には
残すに値するものはなにもない。
There is nothing worth saving
in this reality.
この世は　すでに死んでいる。
This world is already dead.
Hey… This is super bad!
おい　やばいぞ！
４つも　一度にあれを！
Four of them…all at once?
Even if we were to create
an Earth Style Wall,
（黄ツチ）あれでは　土遁障壁を
連合でやっても間に合わん！
it wouldn't be enough!
数が多すぎる。
There are too many of them!
What do we do? Think!
《シカマル：どうする…　考えろ》
あれを　飛雷神で飛ばすのは
一人一つが限度だ。
It would take one person
per each of those
to teleport away using
the Flying Raijin.
四代目と　わしで
２つはいけるとしても→
The Fourth and I can get
to two of them,
but that leaves two others!
Impossible!
他の２つは無理だ。
兄者は？
Where's Elder Brother?
Madara! Could you wait a moment?
（柱間）マダラ！　ちょい待たぬか！
Your comrade is acting up...!
お前の仲間が
やらかしてやがるぞ。
（マダラ）俺たちは　穢土転生だ！
気にすることはない！
We are all Reanimations!
There's no need to worry!
Keep fighting!
このまま続ける！
Do not give up everyone!
皆の者　あきらめるな！
I am with you!
My clones are with you!
俺もおる　俺の分身もおる。
We only need to change
the spheres' trajectories!
玉の軌道さえ変えればよいのだ。
火影たちも手を打ち
海の外へ弾く！
The other Hokage will
also take measures
and repel them across the ocean!
I ask that you all work on putting up
an Earth Style Wall!
皆は　土遁の壁を頼む！
俺は　樹界降誕で
あれを海へ打ち上げ導く！
I'll use the Deep Forest
Emergence to launch
and guide them to
toward the ocean!
そうはさせん！
I won't let you!
《六赤陽陣》
Six Crimson Ray Formation!
A barrier!
結界だ！
お　おい…。
Hey! Don't tell me we're...
これって　まさか　俺たち…。
（柱間）皆を結界で閉じ込め→
He's trapped everyone
inside the barrier,
and he's made it so we can't
expel the Tailed Beast Bombs!
尾獣玉を
外へ弾けなくしたのか。
これで終戦だ。
Endgame.
こうなったら　あれは飛雷神で
結界の外へ飛ばすしかないぞ。
Our only choice now is
to teleport those spheres
outside the barrier using
the Flying Raijin.
四代目　２ついけるか？
Fourth, can you handle two of them?
マーキングができない以上
１つが限界です。
Since we can't mark them,
I can only take one.
方法は　たった一つ…。
There's only one way.
あの…。
We could...
You intend to teleport
the stalk itself outside?
木ごと
外へまるまる飛ばすつもりか？
させると思うか？
You think I'd let you do that?
アンタは誰も救えない。
You can't save anyone!
Dad!
父ちゃん。
I don't know if it will work,
but I've got an idea.
うまくいくかわかんねえけど
考えがあるんだ。
拳を合わせてくれっか？
Will you bump fists with me?
Hey, other half. How ya been?
よう　わしの半身。
元気にしてたかよ？
Do you mind sharing some
of your chakra with me?
ちょいとお前のチャクラを
分けてもらえねえか？
フッ　自分自身に
頼みごとをされるとは→
To be asked a favor from myself
feels a bit weird...
変な感じだな。
Naruto…
ナルト　ソイツは何もできない。
お前の母を守れもしなかった。
Minato's useless,
he can't do anything.
He couldn't even
protect your mom...
Nor his own subordinates.
己の部下も。
明日が　なんの日だか知ってるな？
You know what tomorrow is,
don't you?
It's the anniversary of
Minato and Kushina's deaths.
ミナトとクシナの命日だ。
両親の死んだ日だ。
The day both of your parent's died.
死ねば終わりだ　この世は。
いいか…。
In this world, it's over
when you die.
You see...
Oh, right, which means...
そうだった　なら明日は
俺の生まれた日だ。
it's also the day I was born!
いいか…　終わりじゃねえ。
So you see...
It's not over...
俺がこの世にいる！
'Cuz I exist in this world!
《俺たちのナルトは
本当に強くなったよ…　クシナ》
Our Naruto has
become really strong...
...Kushina.
行くぜ！　父ちゃん！
ああ！
Let's go, Dad!
Yeah!
Thank goodness for
the chakra of you two!
お前らのチャクラがあって
助かったぜ。
It's just as I thought!
思ったとおりだ。
まあな。
Yeah well, the both of us
used to be one, after all.
もともとは　わしたちは
一つだったからな。
それに…。
Plus...those two are
father and son.
コイツらは　親子だしな。
結界に閉じ込めて→
He's planning to trap us
inside this barrier
あれで　結界内を
俺たちごと破壊する気だ！
and blow us up along with it!
どうすんだよ？
What can we do?
《火影たちの結界でも→
The Hokage's barrier didn't let
Tailed Beast Bombs through either…
尾獣玉を通しもしなかった…》
《シカマル：結界を見るかぎり
赤色…。
This barrier is red all over…
I think it's accurate to say that
おそらくは　火影たちの結界と
同等レベルのものと見て間違いない。
this one's likely to be
on par with the Hokages.
俺たちの力で　あれほどの結界を
破るのは無理だ。
With the level of our strength,
it's impossible for us to
smash through it, in which case...
なら…》
《クソッ　何も思い浮かばねえよ
親父！》
Damn it!
Nothing's coming to mind, Dad!
どうする気だ？　ナルト。
What's your plan, Naruto?
今は　ちょっち集中させてくれ。
Just...give me some time to focus...
九喇嘛と考えたことを
説明すっから→
Let me explain what
Kurama and I came up with.
You tell me if
it will work or not, okay?
できるかどうか
判断してくれってばよ。
わかった　すぐに話して。
All right, go ahead!
《ミナト：クシナは　もう会ったかい？
Have you seen him, Kushina?
本当に大きくなったよ　ナルトは》
Our Naruto's really grown up.
《ごめんな　ナルト。
I'm so sorry, Naruto...
ここまで　本当に
いろいろ大変だっただろうに》
I'm sure you must have had it
real tough up until now!
大変なのは　こっからだぜ
父ちゃん。
The real tough part
is about to start, Dad!
（リー）こ…　これは　ナルト君の！
This is Naruto's…!
（サクラ）これ…
消えてなかったんだ。
So…it wasn't depleted?!
（カツユ）皆さんを回復するときに
気づきましたが→
I noticed it when
I was healing everyone, but…
ただ
小さくなっていただけのようです。
It seems it had merely shrunk down.
（チョウジ）これって
さっきよりも強いし　大きいよ。
It's bigger and more powerful
than before!
（キラービー）気づいてるかよ
八っつあん。
Have ya noticed Eight-o?
２人の九尾を感じる　明と暗！
I sense two Nine Tails,
one light and one dark, yo!
（八尾）
こりゃ　九尾だけじゃねえぞ。
This isn't just Nine Tails.
このチャクラで　あの攻撃から
俺たちを守るってのか　ナルト。
You're thinking about
protecting us from that attack
with this chakra, Naruto?
重吾か。
Jugo.
Sasuke, this is looking bad.
Let's get outside of this barrier.
（重吾）サスケ　このままでは　まずい。
結界の外へ出るぞ。
蛇の逆口寄せを使え。
Use the Snake
Reverse Summoning.
そのつもりだ。
That was my plan already.
I'll take you and Naruto
with me.
お前とナルトは一緒に連れていく。
お前らには
俺のチャクラ渡してなかったな。
I haven't given you
any of my chakra yet.
こっち来てくれってばよ。
Get over here, will ya?
フン　そんなチャクラで
どうにかなるのか？
What's your chakra
going to accomplish?
時間がねえ　早くしろ！
There's no time! Just hurry!
忍の者　皆に
チャクラを渡しておったとはのう。
I can't believe he shared
his chakra with every shinobi!
チャクラ量は俺と張るのう。
He's got almost as
much chakra as us!
いや　これは
九尾のチャクラも一緒に…。
No!
Actually, this has
Nine Tails' chakra mixed in!
《オビト：そんなもので
十尾の尾獣玉４つからなる→
That won't help you
withstand the shock wave of
four Ten Tails' Tailed Beast
Bombs exploding together!
共鳴爆破に耐えられはせん。
消し飛べ》
Begone...
これは…。
What?
あ…。
どうなった？
What happened?
またこのチャクラが守ってくれたんだ。
This chakra protected us again!
いや　よく見てみろ。
Not quite, check it out!
（いの）チョウジ　あっち　見て…。
Choji… Look over there.
私たち　結界の外にいる。
We're...
outside the barrier.
（シノ）瞬身の術だな。
It was the Teleportation Jutsu.
（キバ）ナルトのヤツ
こんなことまでできたのか…。
Damn that Naruto!
He's even mastered that too?
（ヒナタ）ナルト君のチャクラだけじゃない。
This isn't just Naruto's chakra.
こりゃ　四代目火影の
飛雷神の術で移動させたな。
He moved everyone using
the Fourth Hokage's Flying Raijin Jutsu!
四代目　お前は　これで→
Fourth…
This is the second time
you've saved all of shinobi-kind.
忍の皆を
二度も救ったことになるな。
ハァ　ハァ…。
失敗の数のほうが多いですから。
I've still failed...
more times than that,
まだまだ　これからです。
so I must continue making up for it.
何をした？
What did you do?
Dad teleported everyone
outside the barrier.
父ちゃんが連合の全員を→
結界の外へ飛ばしたんだってばよ。
Everyone? With that jutsu?
あの術で全員だと？
((俺自身か　俺のチャクラが
間接的にでも触れていなければ→
I can't teleport
anything that I myself,
or my chakra isn't touching,
even indirectly.
(飛ばせない))
How?
どうやって…。
I'd shared Kurama's and
my chakra with everyone earlier.
みんなには　俺と九喇嘛のチャクラを→
前もって渡して
くっつけてあったんだってばよ。
So if Dad, and our chakra
and everybody were to uh...um...
とりあえず　父ちゃんとチャクラと
みんなが　その…。
間接的に…。
そう！
Indirectly…
Right! If we were all
in indirect contact with each other,
間接的に　くっついてりゃ
いいんだから→
it would work.
父ちゃんのチャクラと
俺と九喇嘛のチャクラを→
So, I connected Dad's chakra
with Kurama's and mine.
くっつけてみた！　そんだけ！
That's all!
影分身の原理を利用したのだ。
He used the principle
of Shadow Clones.
己のチャクラを分散し　離しても→
Even if you split up and
disperse your chakra...
少量でも消さずに残しておけば→
as long as you keep even
a little bit there without putting it out...
when the original body infuses
chakra again to regain control,
本体が再びチャクラを
コントロールしようと練ったとき→
分散していたチャクラは
共鳴を起こして連動する。
all the individual chakra bits
begin resonating and link together.
In short, by joining his chakra
with the Fourth's,
つまり　ナルトのチャクラに
四代目のチャクラを接触させ→
Naruto linked the Fourth
to the rest of his chakra
連合の皆に残っているナルトのチャクラと
連結させたということだ。
residing in everyone else.
そうだな？　ナルト。
Right, Naruto?
えっ？　あっ　そうなの？
もういい。
Huh? Is that what I did?
Never mind…
二代目のオッチャンは
俺の影分身のことも詳しいんだな。
Old Man Second, you sure know
a lot about my Shadow Clones too!
I created that jutsu!
わしが作った術だ！
わしの影分身だ！
It's my Shadow Clone Jutsu!
((拳を合わせてくれっか？
（ミナト）ああ。
Will you bump fists with me?
Yeah!
ああ　やってみよう。
Yeah, let's try it!
九尾　いや　九喇嘛の力を借りれば
できないことはない。
There's nothing we can't do
if we borrow Nine Tails'...
I mean, Kurama's power.
よし！　じゃ　４人で
力を合わせてやんぜ！
All right!
Then let's all four of us join forces!
"All four of us," eh?
You treat us like we're human too.
４人か…
わしらを人扱いするとは→
どう育ったらそうなった？　フフフ！
What kind of childrearing
has led to this, eh?
ナルト。
うん？
Naruto…
Huh?!
（ミナト）今のお前と　もっとゆっくり
いろいろ話して…。
I wish there was more time...
to talk to the grown-up you...
男は　いちいち言わなくていい。
もうわかってっから。
Guys don't need to talk!
I already know!
(もう…　母ちゃんのチャクラとは
会ったんだ))
I…already met Mom's chakra.
((クシナ…　もう命が
もちそうにない。
Kushina…my time is running out…
そろそろ八卦封印をやるよ。
I'm going start
the Eight Signed Seal.
俺のチャクラも
ナルトへ少し組み込みたいんだ。
I want to put some of
my chakra in Naruto too.
当分は会えない。　今ナルトに
言いたいことを言っておこう。
It'll be quite a while before
we can see him.
Let's tell him
what we want to say…
（クシナ）ナルト…　好き嫌いしないで→
Naruto…
Don't be picky.
Eat lots and grow strong.
いっぱい食べて大きくなりなさい。
お風呂には
毎日ちゃんと入って温まること。
Make sure you bathe
every day and stay warm.
それと　夜更かししないで
いっぱい寝ること。
Also…don't stay up late.
You need lots of sleep.
それから　お友達を作りなさい。
And…make friends.
たくさんじゃなくていいから→
You don't need a lot of friends.
Just a few…
本当に信頼できる
お友達を数人でいいの。
Ones you can really,
really trust.
お母さんは苦手だったけど→
I wasn't very good at it,
but keep up with your studies
勉強や忍術を
しっかりやりなさい。
and practice your ninjutsu hard.
ただし　得意　不得意が
誰しもあるものだから→
Remember that everyone has
strengths and weaknesses.
あまり　うまくいかなくても
落ち込まないでいいからね。
So don't get too depressed
if you can't do something well.
アカデミーでは　先生や
先輩のことを敬いなさい。
Respect your teachers and
upperclassmen at the Academy.
あ…　それと大切なこと。
Oh, and this is important…
忍の三禁について。
It's about the Three Prohibitions
for a shinobi.
特に　お金の貸し借りには
気をつけること。
Be extra careful about
lending and borrowing money.
任務金は　ちゃんと貯金すること。
Put your mission wages
into your savings account.
お酒は　二十歳になってから。
No alcohol until you're of age.
飲みすぎては体にさわるから
ほどほどにすること。
Too much can ruin your health,
so drink in moderation.
それと　三禁で問題なのが女。
Another Prohibition is women.
母さんは女だから
よくは　わからないけど→
I'm a woman,
so I don't know too much
about this but…
とにかく　この世は
男と女しかいないから。
All you need to remember
is that this world
is made up of men and women.
女の人に興味をもつことに
なっちゃうけど→
So it's only natural to take
an interest in girls…
But just don't get hooked
on bad women.
変な女にひっかからないようにね。
母さんのような人を見つけなさい。
Find someone just like me.
それと　三禁といえば　もう１つ。
Speaking of
the Three Prohibitions,
自来也先生には
気をつけなさいってばね。
Be wary of Jiraiya Sensei.
ハァ…　ハァ…。
ナルト　これから　つらいこと
苦しいことも　いっぱいある。
Naruto…from now on, you're going
to face lots of pain and hardship…
自分をちゃんと持って→
Be true to yourself…
そして夢を持って→
Have a dream…and…
そして　夢を叶えようとする
自信を持って。
もっと　もっと　もっと…。
もっと　本当にいろいろなことを
一緒に教えてあげたい。
もっと一緒にいたい　愛してるよ。
ミナト　ごめん　私ばっかり。
ううん　いいんだ。
ナルト　父さんの言葉は→
(口うるさい母さんと…　同じかな))
((言いてぇことは
口うるせぇ母ちゃんと同じだろ！
(もう　わかってっからな！))
＜歌謡曲黄金時代の→
＜　なんと　２０年分の
年間ベスト３を発表！＞